<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A plain and just account of a most horrid and dismal plague, begun at Rowel, alias Rothwell, in Northampton-shire which hath infected many places round about, or, A faithful narrative of the execrable and noisom errours and the abominable and damnable heresies vented by Richard Davis, pretended pastour to a people at Rowel, and by his emissaries, the shoomakers, joyners, dyers, taylers, weavers, formers, &amp;c. together with a brief account  1. Of his and his parties practices, 2. Visions and revelations, 3. Great boasts, 4. Admission of members into their society, 5. His peoples self-condemnedness, 6. The number and quality of his hearers admired fits, 7. Some queries to the countrey people as matter for further search, 8. An expostulation and advice to the people of Rowel / by Mr. P. Rehakosht ...</title>
            <author>Rehakosht, P.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 101KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B28141</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18471181</idno>
  <idno type="VID">206586</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240876353</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2344</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">18471181</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B28141)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 206586)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1641:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A plain and just account of a most horrid and dismal plague, begun at Rowel, alias Rothwell, in Northampton-shire which hath infected many places round about, or, A faithful narrative of the execrable and noisom errours and the abominable and damnable heresies vented by Richard Davis, pretended pastour to a people at Rowel, and by his emissaries, the shoomakers, joyners, dyers, taylers, weavers, formers, &amp;c. together with a brief account  1. Of his and his parties practices, 2. Visions and revelations, 3. Great boasts, 4. Admission of members into their society, 5. His peoples self-condemnedness, 6. The number and quality of his hearers admired fits, 7. Some queries to the countrey people as matter for further search, 8. An expostulation and advice to the people of Rowel / by Mr. P. Rehakosht ...</title>
                  <author>Rehakosht, P.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: faded, with print show-through and some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Davis, Richard, 1658-1714.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:206586:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:206586:1"/>
            <p>A PLAIN and JUST ACCOUNT Of a Most Horrid and Dismal PLAGUE, BEGUN AT Rowel, <hi>alias</hi> Rothwell, IN NORTHAMPTON-SHIRE Which hath Infected many places round about.</p>
            <p>OR, A Faithful NARRATIVE of the Execrable and Noisom Errours, and the Abominable and Damnable Heresies vented by <hi>Richard Davis,</hi> pretended Pastour to a People at <hi>Rowel;</hi> and by his Emissaries, the <hi>Shoomakers, Joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, Dyers, Taylers, Weavers, Farmers,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>TOGETHER With a Brief Account, 1. Of his, and his Parties <hi>Practices;</hi> 2. <hi>Visions, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations;</hi> 3. Great <hi>Boasts;</hi> 4. <hi>Admission of Members into</hi> their Society; 5. His Peoples <hi>Self-Condemn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dness;</hi> 6. The <hi>Number</hi> and <hi>Quality</hi> of his Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers admired <hi>Fits;</hi> 7. Some <hi>Queries</hi> to the Countrey People as Matter for further search; 8. An <hi>Expostulation</hi> and <hi>Advice</hi> to the People of <hi>Rowel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By Mr.</hi> P. REHAKOSHT, <hi>&amp;c. Inhabiting on the East side of the Seat of the Plague.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Quae est enim pejor mors animae quàm libertas Erroris.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>August. contra Donatist. Tom. 2. Ep. 166.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Author, 1692.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:206586:2"/>
            <head>A Plain and Just ACCOUNT Of a Most Horrid and Dismal PLAGUE, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THOSE Errours that strike at the very foundation of the true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and that plainly sink Persons into Sou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>-ruining mistakes about their Estate and Condition for Eternity (as many of these do) the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle <hi>Peter</hi> calls (in the 2d Epistle, 2d Chapter, and 1st verse) <hi>Damnable Heresies;</hi> which <hi>False Teachers</hi> shall bring in Privily, or undiscern'd by the the Common (though well-meaning) Hearers. Thus <hi>Richard Davis</hi> and his Emissaries have privily insinuated their Damnable Heresies, under the Colour and Pretence of <hi>Purer Gospel,</hi> than the Country had before heard; and <hi>greater Light</hi> than they had before enjoy'd. This specious pretence the ignorant People are wonderfully deluded by; and now their cry is <hi>[All that Mr.</hi> Davis <hi>says is pure Gospel]</hi> and <hi>[they that speak against Mr.</hi> Davis, <hi>speak against the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel;]</hi> and [he, and his Preachers, are <hi>wonderful Men;</hi> and <hi>Men of greater light than others.</hi>] But though their Doctrines please the corrupt hearts of Men, yet seeing they are contrary to God's Word, as this Narrative will evidence, 'tis a sign they have no light in them; <hi>Isaiah</hi> 8.20. <hi>To the Law, and to the Testimony; if they speak not according to this word, 'tis because there is no light in them.</hi> The presumptuous Faith they do by these Doctrines build up their Followers in, doth as effectually tend to their ruine, as a course of open Prophaneness and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baucheries, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.22, 23. <hi>Luke</hi> 13.27. Therefore the Apostle <hi>Peter</hi> might well call such <hi>Damnable Heresies.</hi> And how evidently do these <hi>Davisites deny the Lord that bought them, while they oppose so many of his Truths;</hi> (as may be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from what follows) and <hi>while they practically deny him a Throne among them,</hi> setting up their own fancies, and lusts, to guide and rule them in matters of Doctrine, and Practice both; instead of submitting themselves to the plain meaning and design of Christ in his word; <hi>and withall, to shelter and hide their wickedness, they pervert and wrest many of Christ's blessed Records,</hi> as Matth. 12.39. <hi>There shall no Sign be given, but that of the Prophet</hi> Jonas, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To oppose and throw down the use of all marks and signs of Grace. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.28. of God's cutting short his work of Judgment upon the <hi>Jewish</hi>-Nation; they pervert to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:206586:2"/> throw down all common and all preparatory works of the Spirit, Illumination Conviction, <hi>&amp;c. Matth.</hi> 10.34. <hi>R. Davis</hi> wrested at <hi>Thorp,</hi> to vindicate his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding all Societies where he goes (as much as in him lies.) Likewise <hi>John</hi> 7.37. and many more. The Reader may by this Treatise quickly perceive also how near a-kin these <hi>Davisites</hi> be, to that other deluded Party in the Kingdom, who think none have the Spirit but they, none are acquainted with the Eternal Truth but themselves; when in the mean time we find none are run into meer fancies like them; none are more effectually turned (by Satan's wiles) from the only Rule of Faith and Life, God's written word, than they are. You may please to observe, Reader, further, that the Devil has gotten <hi>R. Davis</hi> and his Emissaries to <hi>Preach down all Doubts and Questio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ings of their State,</hi> as <hi>Legall,</hi> and <hi>a Spirit of Bondage,</hi> and <hi>to Preach</hi> up the <hi>Highest Confidence instantly.</hi> These things many of us have been Ear-witnesses of, as well as of what was before mentioned. But hereby they stave off their People from all <hi>Examination</hi> of their Hearts and Ways by Scripture Rules, and cause them to avoid all suspicion of their state and way, and all Holy jealousie; perverting 1 <hi>Epist.</hi> of <hi>John,</hi> 4.18. <hi>Perfect Love casts out Fear,</hi> to wit, slavish fear; but they wrest it to cast out all Godly fear, though this is enjoyned, <hi>Romans</hi> 11.20, 21. <hi>Be not high minded, but fear: Take heed lest he spare not thee, Heb.</hi> 12.28. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> They farther plead against <hi>Examination,</hi> &amp;c. thus, pretending <hi>['tis a running to our own Works;]</hi> whereas we only plead for the practice of Good works; and that the Scripture declares by such fruits the truth of Grace and Regeneration may be evidenced; but we do as much, and (we humbly hope) more truly abhor any dependance on our own Works, Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or Graces, than they under all their Delusive Pretences do; and can say, we adore, and live daily upon the rich Grace of God in Christ, as the great joy of our Souls, and our only Consolation for Eternity; as well as our safety, strength, and comfort in time. But we earnestly seek <hi>[the advancing the Soveraign Grace of God in Christ, according to the word of Christ, and not according to the fancies of Men]</hi> We abhor making the fancies of Men the measures of Divine Grace, as the <hi>Davisites</hi> apparently and wretchedly do; and therefore we declare, and plead against them.</p>
            <p>Now, Reader, you may see on the one hand, how Satan has gotten these poor deluded Creatures into his Snare so effectually, as he may suggest almost what he will, and lead them how he will, and they dance blindfold after his Pipe most rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily, though it be down towards the Bottomless Pit.</p>
            <p>You may see likewise, on the other hand, the occasion of this Narrative; and the real intent, and design thereof; 'tis to p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t forth a hand to stop others that are ready to dance away to Hell with them; as also to try whether there may not be some of God's Elect among them, who shall be reclaimed, though hitherto be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witched in by Satan, and these his Agents: and shall be made to abhor those Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swasions, and Practices, when they see what a Fool's Paradise they have been flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered with. May this Narrative prove successful for these Ends, to the Lord shall be given the whole Glory of so great a Mercy to them, and so good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n effect as is here aimed at.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:206586:3"/>
            <p>Great Care and Pains have been taken in this matter, that the Reader may have the most just and faithful accompt of these things; and yet likewise that the <hi>Davisites</hi> may not have the least tittle of injustice done them. Indeed many things are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted out of tenderness to them, though we have sufficient assurances of the truth of them. And yet we cannot but acquaint the Reader, that they have been often in all meekness and love admonished, advised, warned, and confuted from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures by some or other of our number, almost weekly, and daily; yet they conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue so obstinate, and passionate for their way, that no means we have hitherto been capable of using, can reclaim them; therefore we conclude, we are bound in Conscience, to lay their Principles, Pretences, Practices, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> together in this publick Compend. for the warning of those that are in danger of this infection. Yet 'tis needful to do others that Justice, as to let the Reader know, who else have appeared against these Abominations.</p>
            <p n="1">I. The Dissenting Ministers of <hi>London,</hi> have by Letter, and in Discourses with <hi>R. Davis</hi> (when they had him under examination) declared against such Principles and Practices as they heard, and have been many ways assured he is guilty of Infecting and Disturbing the Country with: Several of which they name in their Letter, and are here put down among the rest. First, They have condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his Principles, as 1. Grosly unsound. 2. Plainly <hi>Antinomian.</hi> 3. As apt to bring in Licentiousness in Practice. And, 4. Also ungrounded comfort. 5. As a full opposing the Government of Christ. And, 6. An opposing the fitness of a Gospel Ministry to the saving Designs of our Redeemer.</p>
            <p>Secondly, His Practices they Condemn, as 1. irregular. 2. Very scandalous. 3. Injurious to their Christian Profession. 4. As an abuse to God's Mercy, and to the Clemency of our Rulers.</p>
            <p>Therefore they had him before them lately with a design, after charging him with these things, to silence him▪ (if possible) but he made Lies his refuge, 'till he saw he could defend himself no longer, and then he sham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med them off thus, by requiring his Accusers to be brought face to face; which was concluded to be done against their next meeting; but he took his opportunity in the mean while to slip into <hi>Northampton-shire,</hi> and so came no more at them, as we hear from various certain hands. Their sending into the Country for Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences, is only labour lost; <hi>R. D.</hi> can show them the trick of a Jugler, thus fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well hur Examiners, and now catch hur who can.</p>
            <p n="2">II. The Ministers in the Country all about him, both Conformists, and Non-conformists, have Preached down these Errours; and some of them almost every Lord's Day, as their Auditories need; shewing the People the Soul-ruining tendency of them, and their contrariety to the plain meaning of God's word.</p>
            <p n="3">III. Mr. <hi>Holcraft</hi> (lately deceased) abhorred these Errours, having himself heard Mr. <hi>Davis</hi> deliver some of them. But would you have it in Mr. <hi>Holcraft</hi>'s own sense, take it thus. When several of Mr. <hi>H's.</hi> People went to him to desire a dismission, Mr. <hi>H.</hi> answered in this manner, <hi>[I am willing to give you a dismission, if you will set down with such a one, or such a one</hi> (naming the Ministers) <hi>who are sound in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:206586:3"/> the Faith:]</hi> They replyed after this sort; <hi>[No, we are for Men of greater Light]</hi> Mr. <hi>H.</hi> 'tis said, upon hearing this, fell down in a swoon, having been in a lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guishing Condition a long while before, as we know. But when he was recovered, he added [<hi>What have I spent my days, and my strength, and hazarded my Life to direct you in the ways of truth, and are you now turning aside to whimsies? I'll give you none.</hi> And, <hi>I am sorry that I did not publickly oppose Mr.</hi> Davis <hi>in the Congregation at</hi> Tafts.] This Account is received from some well acquainted with Mr. <hi>H.</hi> and is here inserted as a standing and Publick Testimony for Mr. <hi>H.</hi> but <hi>against those of his People that are now so giddily running after R.D.</hi> and his Emissa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, contrary to their late Pastors mind.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. When two Grave Ministers, and a Justice of Peace Discoursed <hi>R. D.</hi> to see whether it were possible to bring him to a quiet, peaceable, and loving agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with Neighbour Ministers, urging various Arguments, which we might give the Reader in particular (would it not protract the Introduction too much) endeavouring also to give a tender check to his disturbing Practices. <hi>R. D.</hi> made answer <hi>[Christ came to bring a Sword upon Earth, and not Peace;]</hi> one of the Ministers shewed him, how he misinterpreted those words of our Lord; but all would not prevail with him. This Account we have from some of the Ear Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses, very Judicious and Pious Persons.</p>
            <p>This <hi>R. D.</hi> has made great disturbances in the Country, and yet endeavours to colour over all, and flatter his Hearers with this deceitful Lye, <hi>[That 'tis the Gospel makes all the Differences:]</hi> The same he told those Ministers. Here the Reader may observe how Blasphemously he charges his own wickednesses upon the Gospel. And what his wicked Disturbing Doctrines and Practices be, we come now particularly to relate.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The <hi>PRINCIPLES</hi> and <hi>DOCTRINES</hi> of R. Davis.</head>
               <p n="1">I. <hi>WHatever is supernatural, is Saving-Grace.</hi> This he delivered on <hi>Kimbolton</hi> side. Some very judicious Hearers discoursed him after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards about it.</p>
               <p>This Assertion of his, destroys all the common works of the Spirit, and is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to <hi>Luke</hi> 8. <hi>v.</hi> 13, 14. Where our Lord assures us, that there is a Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary Faith, which though supernatural, yet is not Saving. And contrary to <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.22, 23. <hi>Prophecying in the Name of Christ, and Casting out Devils, and doing many wonderful works.</hi> The Gifts and Power for these are Supernatural, and yet not Saving, for our Lord declares he will disown them. <hi>Judas</hi> his Gift of working Miracles, and <hi>Balaam's</hi> Gift of Prophecy, were both Supernatural, yet neither of them Saving: Then this Principle will not serve to prove, that the high confidence of <hi>R. D</hi>'s Adherents is Saving Faith; but rather shews his Policy to bolster them up in such a conceit, as they may never question their Salvation.</p>
               <p n="2">II. <hi>Our Lord Christ Preached not terrour.</hi> This <hi>R. D.</hi> asserted in his Sermon at <hi>Rowell,</hi> as is testified by Eminent Ear-Witnesses, who further observed also, that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:206586:4"/> before he had done, he himself preached Damnation to Unbelievers. Thus he is inconsistent with himself, and hath impudently, and abominably contradicted that 23d Chapter of <hi>Matth.</hi> where our Lord Christ Preaches Woe after Woe; <hi>Woe unto you Scribes, and Pharisees, Hypocrites,</hi> vers. 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 19, 23, 24, 25, 26, 27, 28, 29, 31, 33, 35, 36, 37, 38, 39. It contradicts also Matth. 7.22, 23. <hi>Many will say to me in that day, Lord, Lord, have we not Prophesied in thy Name, in thy Name cast out Devils, and in thy Name done many wonderful works? Then will I profess unto them, I know you not, depart from me, ye that work iniquity.</hi> See also Matth. 11.21. <hi>Woe unto thee</hi> Chorazin, <hi>and</hi> Bethsaida, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.15. <hi>If ye forgive not Men their Trespasses, neither will your Father forgive your Trespasses.</hi> There our Lord Christ preacheth terrour to his own beloved Disciples; as also in <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.20. <hi>For I say unto you, that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept your Righteousness exceeds the Righteousness of the</hi> Scribes <hi>and</hi> Pharisees, <hi>ye shall in no case enter into the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> Scores of other Scriptures op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose this Doctrine, but <hi>R. D.</hi> can easily overlook them when they serve not his turn. Who so blind as those <hi>that will not see? By this you may very plainly dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern, how absolutely contrary</hi> R. D's <hi>Gospel is unto our dear Lord Christ's Gospel: And the following Doctrines of</hi> R. D. <hi>will further manifest it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">III. <hi>To Preach marks of Sanctification is a Doctrine of an Old Covenant strain.</hi> This <hi>R. D.</hi> declared in a Sermon on <hi>Cambridge</hi> side. But Mr. <hi>Holcraft,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Worden</hi> Ministers, hearing him, could not bear it without manifesting their dislike thereof. This Doctrine of his, is contrary to what our Lord, and his Apostles both set up. <hi>First,</hi> our Blessed Lord himself preached up <hi>Marks and Signs of Grace, and Sanctification,</hi> John 13.35. <hi>By this shall all Men know that ye are my Disciples, if ye have love one to another.</hi> John 15.14. <hi>Ye are my Friends, if ye do whatsoever I command you.</hi> John 14. v. 21. <hi>He that hath my Commandments, and keepeth them, he it is that loveth me,</hi> &amp;c. Here's a sign of true Love. <hi>John</hi> 8.31. <hi>If ye continue in my word, then are ye my Disciples indeed. Secondly,</hi> his Apostles deliver'd marks of Sanctification, 1 <hi>Epist. John,</hi> 2. <hi>Ch.</hi> 3d and 5th verses, <hi>Hereby we know that we do know him, if we keep his Commandments.</hi> v. 5. <hi>But whoso keepeth his word, in him verily is the Love of God perfected: hereby we know that we are in him.</hi> What can be plainer, if the <hi>Davisites</hi> were not willfully blind? So, 1 John 3.10, 14. <hi>In this the Children of God are manifest,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever doth not Righteousness is not of God, neither he that loveth not his Brother.</hi> verse 14. <hi>We know that we have passed from Death unto Life, because we Love the Brethren.</hi> See also Rom. 8.9, 10, 11, 13, 14. 2 Corinth. 5.17. 2 Cor. 13.5. Galat. 5.24. James 2.17, 18. 1 Pet. 1.22, 23. The Apostle <hi>James</hi> call us to try our Faith, by <hi>Marks, the Fruits, and Effects.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>One would wonder what Translation <hi>R. D.</hi> useth, that he can find none of these in his Bible.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. <hi>Sanctification is no Evidence of Justification.</hi> This <hi>R. D.</hi> delivered in his Sermon at <hi>Cambridge.</hi> But 'tis sufficiently contrary to <hi>Romans</hi> 8.1. <hi>There is therefore now no Condemnation to them which are in Christ Jesus.</hi> But how shall
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:206586:4"/> we know who are these justified Persons? Answer by their Sanctification <hi>[who walk not after the Flesh, but after the Spirit]</hi> Galat. 5.24. <hi>They that are Christs, have crucified the Flesh, with the Affections and Lusts.</hi> See also the Scriptures mentioned under the last head, which this Doctrine plainly contradicts. Doubtless <hi>Sanctification</hi> bears a harsh sound in <hi>R. D</hi>'s ears; 'tis a sign he has still a touch of his old temper, that would not bear such preciseness. As his People confess, <hi>that</hi> (before his Conversion, say they) <hi>he was as vile a Wretch as lives;</hi> but when <hi>Dicky</hi> is throughly Converted, he will not shrink so much at the Doctrine of Sanctification, as now he does.</p>
               <p n="5">V. <hi>Zeal is to be preferred before Judgment.</hi> Here <hi>R. D.</hi> nicks it indeed; for when they swallow this, he can lead them like a Bear by the nose, whither he pleases. This he deliver'd on <hi>Kimbolton</hi> side, testified by a Minister, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> hearers. But Reader have a care of it, remember the Proverb, [you had as good eat the Devil himself, as the Broth he is boyl'd in:] <hi>R. D.</hi> is sure of all he catches in this Noose. Now be but Zealous for the <hi>Rowelian</hi> Cause, and never question but you shall be saved, as sure as the Ramping Wench of <hi>Archester,</hi> concerning whose Salvation Brother <hi>J. F.</hi> is so confident, be she never so much Ramp, or Thief, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> See the 3d Instance under <hi>Admission.</hi> Here mind, Reader, what you might gain, if you will but be zealous for the <hi>Rowelian</hi> Cause. Yet stay a little, and see how bravely this Doctrine agrees with <hi>Romans</hi> 10.2, 3. where <hi>Paul</hi> is so bold as to Condemn it. The <hi>Jews</hi> had a Zeal of God, but not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to knowledge; and so set up their own Righteousness, and submitted not unto the Righteousness of God. <hi>Acts</hi> 22.3, 4, 5. and <hi>Philip.</hi> 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6. Where <hi>Paul</hi> shews the miserable fruits of Zeal without Judgment. By this Doctrin <hi>R. D.</hi> makes <hi>Saul</hi> the Persecutor a better Man than <hi>Paul</hi> the Convert; prefers Persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors before Judicious Saints. But who does not see that this Doctrine has a Pope in its belly, and will help on his People with a Catholick Courage?</p>
               <p n="6">VI. <hi>The Law sets Persons a thousand times farther off from Christ.</hi> This <hi>R. D.</hi> belched out in his Sermon at <hi>New-Market,</hi> contrary to <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.7. <hi>Is the Law sin? God forbid: nay, I had not known sin, but by the Law.</hi> This <hi>R. D.</hi> would keep Persons ignorant of Sin, but how will they ever value and prize Christ then? He would fain hide Sin also, by his great cry about Faith, and then his People are fit for all Secret Debaucheries, that the Countrey may not cry shame of, if they can but keep their own Counsel. <hi>Romans</hi> 3.31. <hi>Do we then make void the Law through faith? God forbid: yea, we establish it.</hi> By this Doctrine you may understand how great an Enemy <hi>R. D.</hi> is to the Law of God, which <hi>Paul</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares to be Holy, Just, and Good, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.12. And is it not a sign he is carnally minded then, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.7. declares?</p>
               <p n="7">VII. <hi>Such as Preach up Qualifications, are Legal Preachers, keep People in Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, and are Enemies to their Comfort.</hi> This <hi>R. D.</hi> deli er'd at <hi>Wellembor.</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from good ear Testimony. By this <hi>R. D.</hi> makes our Lord, and his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles, Legal Preachers, and Enemies to Peoples comfort. But who sees <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut what abominable Blasphemy he is <hi>in effect</hi> guilty of? <hi>First,</hi> our Lord Christ
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:206586:5"/> Preached up those Qualifications, <hi>Mark</hi> 1.15. <hi>Repent ye, and believe the Gospel. Mat.</hi> 11.28. such as labour and are heavy laden, and are willing to take his yoke upon them. <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.12, 13. such as are sensible of their soul-sickness, and their sinfulness, such the Lord invites. 2. His Apostles Preached up those Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications, <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.8, 9, 10. <hi>Draw nigh to God. Cleanse your hands. Purifie your hearts. Be afflicted, and mourn, and weep. Humble your selves in the sight of the Lord.</hi> 1 Joh. 1.9. <hi>If we confess our sins, he'll forgive,</hi> &amp;c. Thus sense of sin, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation for sin, sight of their need of Christ, renunciation of sin, confession, sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission to his yoke, our Lord Christ and his Apostles Preached up. But <hi>R. D.</hi> loves to sleep on a soft Pillow, and cares not that any should awaken him or his people, therefore he finds out a way to discard such rousing Qualifications, as go so severely against the grain. Of this see more under Head the 17th.</p>
               <p n="8">8th. <hi>A sense of sin enrages persons against Christ:</hi> This he also asserted as is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed by one of his own hearers. This is desperately contrary to the Scriptures mentioned under the last Head. See what a secure sleep <hi>R. D.</hi> endeavours to get his people into, he would have no sense of sin to come to disturb them. But how unavoidably must such souls perish. See also Head 17.</p>
               <p n="9">9th. <hi>People must beware of three sorts of Preachers, Babylonish, Graceless, and such as mix the Law with the Gospel.</hi> This <hi>R. D.</hi> deliver'd at <hi>Wellemborough.</hi> By this third sort, he means all the Ministers thereabout, and in all other parts of the Kingdom, that go not his way. For thus his people understand him and speak it out plainer. <hi>R. D.</hi> himself at <hi>Kimbolton June</hi> 14. declared to a Minister (who told him of the Elders abhorring his Doctrines, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) this, as his sense concerning them, [I neither care for you, nor for the Elders, for they are all <hi>Arminians, Ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raldists</hi> and <hi>Baxterians,</hi> and so are you an <hi>Arminian.</hi>] This is attested by very judicious Ear-testimony. Another time <hi>R.D.</hi> said, <hi>That Mr.</hi> S. (whom many of us know to be a very pious Minister) <hi>is an enemy to pure Gospel, and to the Lord Christ, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver converted one soul.</hi> And <hi>R. D</hi>'s principal Abettor at <hi>W.</hi> has declared, <hi>He has heard</hi> London. <hi>Ministers, but never heard the Gospel preached before he heard Mr. Davis.</hi> The same person asserted concerning a reverend Minister in <hi>Leicestershire. That he is a dry stick of wood, in comparison of Mr.</hi> Davis. These things are so certain, and and abundantly known, that hereby you may understand the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this Caution of <hi>R. D. And his and his Parties sense of other Ministers.</hi> But is not this manifestly contrary to <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.3. <hi>Let nothing be done through strife, or vain glory, but in lowliness of mind, let each esteem other better than themselves.</hi> Rom. 12.10. <hi>Be kindly affectioned one to another with brotherly love, in honour preferring one another.</hi> Rom. 13.7. <hi>Render to all their dues,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>honour to whom honour is due.</hi> 1 Cor. 3.4. <hi>While one saith, I am of Paul, and another, I am of Apollo, are ye not carnal.</hi> But the best way for <hi>R. D.</hi> to set up himself in his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple's good opinion, is to tread down others. And to get a Dog hang'd, you must cry he is mad.</p>
               <p n="10">10th. <hi>Saints under the Old Testament had no spiritual life, but in doing.</hi> You might, <hi>Dicky,</hi> as well have said, <hi>none at all,</hi> Rom. 3.20. This <hi>R. Davis</hi> held forth at <hi>Wellembor.</hi> But 'tis wretchedly contrary to <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.17, 18. See also <hi>verse</hi> 9.14, 15: We are blessed (in this Gospel-day) with believing <hi>Abraham:</hi> His blessing is come upon us Gentiles: And that blessing is the Eternal Inheritance,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:206586:5"/> and that Inheritance is not of the Law, but God gave it to <hi>Abraham</hi> by Promise. And <hi>Vers.</hi> 8. the Scripture (or God speaking in the Scripture) Preached the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel to <hi>Abraham.</hi> And <hi>vers.</hi> 21, 22. <hi>Life could not come by the Law. Therefore this Doctrine of</hi> R. D. <hi>sinks all the Old Testament Saints to Hell at once.</hi> How contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is it also to <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.13, 23, 24, 25. <hi>Righteousness through faith was imputed to Abraham:</hi> This is recorded for our comfort: It was not written for his sake alone, that it was imputed to him, (<hi>vers.</hi> 24.) but <hi>for us</hi> also, <hi>to whom it shall be imputed,</hi> if we believe. Thus <hi>Abraham</hi> was saved by the same Righteousness we are, the Righteousness of Christ imputed to us upon our believing: <hi>Abraham</hi> is set forth as an instance and pattern of Justification by Faith, which is common to all his Spiritual seed, Believers.</p>
               <p n="11">11th. <hi>They had no more comfort than while they were sorrowing, weeping and mourning:</hi> This he added to the former Doctrine in the same Sermon: But 'tis contrary to <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.56. <hi>Your Father Abraham rejoyced to see my day, and he saw it, and was glad:</hi> This Text proves <hi>Abraham</hi> was a Believer in Christ, as the <hi>Messias</hi> then to come; and that he had joy in believing. <hi>Habakkuk</hi> had joy in the Lord, <hi>Chap.</hi> 3. <hi>vers.</hi> 17, 18, 19. <hi>Although the fig-tree shall not blossom,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>yet will I rejoyce in the Lord: I will joy in the God of my Salvation. The Lord is my strength,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Hezekiah</hi> had joy, <hi>Isa.</hi> 38.19, 20. <hi>The living he shall praise thee, as I do this day,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>The Lord was ready to save me, therefore we will sing my songs.</hi> 'Tis well you did not live in their days <hi>R. D.</hi> to be put to so much penance, for the title of a Saint, as you pretend they were. But doth not <hi>David</hi> triumph in the Lord, in the 27th. Psalm throughout; and in many other Psalms, which the Reader may conclude <hi>R. D.</hi> had lost out of his Bible, or never minded them, for else how could he so impudently contradict them. Some Intelligent and Pious Hearers discoursed him civilly, and tenderly about this tenth and eleventh Doctrine, and urged <hi>Hebr.</hi> 1. against them; but R. <hi>Davis</hi> replied, <hi>That faith in</hi> Hebr. 11. <hi>was only a faith that helped the Old Testament Saints to do great works:</hi> Yet we know R. D. your <hi>Faith and Oyl</hi> both put together, cannot help you so much therefore you must needs be a wonderful weak Believer in comparison of them. These Christians farther argued, <hi>Isaiah</hi> spake of Christ's Glory, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But R.D. triumphed over them with this answer, <hi>Isaiah did not know what he said:</hi> This made another person in the Neighbourhood conclude, at hearing thereof, <hi>That in</hi> R. D<hi>'s account</hi> Isaiah <hi>must needs be either a fool or a mad man. R.</hi> D. hears of this Conclusion, and at his return to <hi>Wellembr.</hi> in his Sermon, to vindicate himself, he charges <hi>R. P.</hi> the wrong person with this false Accusation, <hi>That he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dustriously spread this report that</hi> R. D. <hi>should say,</hi> Isaiah <hi>was mad.</hi> Besides R.D. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solves he will not leave them so, and therefore he adds (as judicious Ear-testimony assures, this following Head.</p>
               <p n="12">12th. <hi>The Devil of Lying has filled the tongues of all Professors:</hi> But 'tis a wonder how R. D. himself escapes from being numbered among them, seeing he makes the greatest noise about Profession: 'Tis true, the Frier preacheth against Stearing, when he has a Pudding in his Sleeve.</p>
               <p n="13">13th. <hi>All the Churches in</hi> England <hi>are gone a whoring from Christ at this day▪</hi> This <hi>R. Davis</hi> asserted on <hi>Thorp</hi> side: Testified by such as were present at his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livering it: Surely R. D. meant all besides <hi>Rowel</hi> Church, else he condemns him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:206586:6"/> and his own people. Here R. D. plays the <hi>Billinsgate</hi> Scold; where she that cries <hi>Whore</hi> first, gets the start and the day of the rest, though she her self be the only Whore in the Company.</p>
               <p n="14">14th. <hi>Sinners must come to Christ and be united to him in all their sin and filth:</hi> This he also preached at <hi>Wellembr.</hi> and explained it thus, <hi>A poor Girl comes to beg Bread at a great mans door, saith the great man, I'le give you Bread enough, if you'll marry my Son: says the poor Wench, Let me go put off my filthy rags, and then I'le come: No, saith he, you must marry him as you are.</hi> These received from Intelligent Ear-witness. This Doctrine is contrary to 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17, 18. <hi>Wherefore come out from among them, and be ye separate, saith the Lord, and touch not the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean thing, and I will receive you,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.37, 38. <hi>Repent and be Baptized</hi> Luk. 15.10, 18, 19. <hi>There is joy in the presence of the Angels over one sinner that repenteth. Father, I have sinned against Heaven,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and am no more worthy to be called thy Son.</hi> But as long as such Doctrines as this, are coverings for <hi>R.D</hi>'s old Inclinations, you must not find fault with them.</p>
               <p n="15">15th. <hi>There are five times wherein Christ intercedes more for his Elect, than at other times; and one time is a time of greater sinning.</hi> Two Ministers heard him deliver this, and discoursed with him about it. 'Tis contrary to the nature of Christ's Intercession, which is an appearing in Heaven for us, and a presenting his will to the Father in such a Divine way, as he may be said rather virtually, than verbal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to intercede: He so presents the sufficiency of his satisfaction, as that by vertue thereof ten thousand Prayers shall be heard at once; but if he pleaded <hi>Orally</hi> (as that Doctrine supposes), then while one case is pleading, thousands and ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sands of others on the earth must wait; and before one thousand be pleaded, seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of the others in extremity may perish. Yea, Christ's Intercession is not only a kind of powerful and effectual representation of his will, as is deducible from <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.24. <hi>Father I will that those,</hi> &amp;c. But such as that he doth together with the Father <hi>execute</hi> that joint will (the Fathers and his) <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.13, 14. <hi>Whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ye shall ask in my name that I will do.</hi> Vers. 14. <hi>If ye shall ask any thing in my name, I will do it.</hi> Neither is that expression, <hi>Advocate,</hi> in 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.1. to be strained, for the same word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is Translated <hi>Comforter,</hi> or any one call<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d in for assistance. 'Tis applied also to the Holy Ghost, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.16, 26. and <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.26. See the Original. And whereas 'tis said, <hi>I will pray the Father,</hi> in <hi>vers.</hi> 16. We must understand it with <hi>Grotius,</hi> &amp;c. thus, <hi>Christ doth not pray with tears and supplications, as on earth, but according to that authority which he hath in Heaven, not in a</hi> servile way of intreaty, but in the vertue of his merit. Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocates on earth do not sit down at the right hand of the Judges, as Christ in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven doth▪ <hi>Hebr.</hi> 8.1. and 9.24. 30. <hi>Ch.</hi> 12, 13. He sits down expecting the vertue of his merit to be applied to Believers; yea, he hath all power given into his hand for that end, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.18. <hi>All power is given to me in Heaven and in Earth.</hi> But why, <hi>I will pray,</hi> and yet in 13, <hi>&amp;</hi> 14. <hi>I will do it.</hi> We answer in the words of a Learned Divine, 'Tis to shew he is <hi>Man</hi> and <hi>Mediator;</hi> he some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times speaks after the manner of men, and sometimes speaks as God, to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate both Natures in his Person. But still the whole of his Intercession must be understood, suitable to his High Glorious, and <hi>Authoritative</hi> condition in Heaven.</p>
               <p n="16">16th. We are <hi>Actually justified from Eternity:</hi> This <hi>R.</hi> D. delivered at <hi>Thorp,</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>tified by several Ear-witnesses.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:206586:6"/>2. <hi>We are justified ever since the Death of Christ:</hi> This <hi>R.</hi> D. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ivered at <hi>Cambridge.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>We are actually justified before Faith:</hi> This on <hi>Cayso side.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Justification by Faith is only a manifestation of it in our own Consciences.</hi> On <hi>Cayso</hi> side; receiv'd from Ear-testimony.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>God loved us from eternity, and as much before conversion, as after conversion:</hi> At <hi>Bedford:</hi> Attested by a Minister, Ear-witness.</p>
               <p>Here the Reader may observe, when a Country Divine had beaten him out of one hold, he shifts to another: But all are contrary to <hi>Ephes.</hi> 2.13. <hi>But now in Christ Jesus ye who were sometimes afar of, are made nigh by the blood of Christ.</hi> Ver. 3.5. <hi>We were by nature children of wrath, even as others. Even when we were dead in sin, God</hi> (who is rich in mercy) <hi>hath quickned us,</hi> Joh. 3.18. They who do not believe are in a state of condemnation and wrath already. Then persons cannot be in a state of Actual Justification till they believe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1. <hi>Being justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by faith.</hi> Col. 1.21. <hi>You that were sometimes alienated and enemies in your mind by wicked works, yet now hath he reconciled.</hi> Therefore persons are not actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally justified from eternity, yea that were to be justified before they had a <hi>Being,</hi> and before they <hi>Sinned;</hi> and were conceived and born in a justified state; contrary to the Texts mentioned, and to <hi>Psal.</hi> 51.5. <hi>I was shapen in iniquity, and in sin did my mother conceive me,</hi> saith <hi>David.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And when <hi>R.D.</hi> slipt down from Eternity to the death of Christ, that was but a trifle with him, for he can <hi>say and unsay</hi> in the same Pulpit, as at <hi>Northampton, Bricksworth,</hi> and <hi>Kimbolton;</hi> yea in the same Sermon, as at <hi>Rowel.</hi> Head, 2d.</p>
               <p n="17">17. <hi>[There must be no works, because God rested in Christ, and so do Believers in Christ.]</hi> Observe what <hi>R. D.</hi> urges here; <hi>[the throwing away Works:]</hi> and you see how roundly he comes up to the business, and what profound reason he brings for the proof of it, or rather to delude his Hearers into the belief of it, that there must be no works.</p>
               <p>'Tis true, <hi>Bear</hi> (the quondam Apothecary of <hi>Oney</hi>) one of <hi>R. D</hi>'s. accomplices, expressed it in his Sermon thus, <hi>[Down with Works, down with the Law.]</hi> This <hi>Bear</hi> roared it out bravely; and <hi>R. D.</hi> is not behind hand with him, for he has helped the <hi>Bear</hi> to a Rich Wife, the Widdow <hi>Biggs,</hi> to gratifie the <hi>Bear</hi> for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming his Champion. (Though this <hi>Bear</hi> roared it out almost as plain in his Sermon at <hi>Northampton</hi> [when he called <hi>Conviction of Sin a Carnal and Sinful Work.</hi>] Whereas the Scripture tells us 'tis the work of the Holy Spirit of God, <hi>John</hi> 16.8. <hi>When he is come, he will reprove the World of Sin.</hi> But surely the work of the Holy Ghost is not Carnal and Sinful; but rather <hi>Dicky</hi>'s Bear roared out Blasphemy.) And might not <hi>R. D.</hi> and his Bear both have expressed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves thus, as well; [Down with all those Scriptures where our Lord Christ pleads for works.] <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.20. <hi>For I say unto you except your Righteousness exceeds the Righteousness of the Scribes,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ye shall not enter into the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> verse 44. <hi>But I say unto you, love your Enemies, bless them that curse you, do good to them that hate you.</hi> verse 48. <hi>Be ye perfect,</hi> &amp;c. Matth. 7.21. <hi>Not he that saith Lord, Lord, shall enter into Heaven, but he that doth the will of my Father.</hi> And [down with those S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>riptures that plead for <hi>Conviction of Sin.</hi>] John 16.7, 8.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:206586:7"/> Rom. 7.7. Romans 3.20. <hi>By the Law is the knowledge of Sin.</hi> The Law, as the means which the holy Spirit makes use of 2 Corinth. 7.9, 10, 11. <hi>I rejoyce that ye sorrowed to Repentance,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Letter helped to <hi>convince them</hi> of their guilt by Incest, but this Conviction was followed with <hi>Repentance to Salvation.</hi> See more, <hi>Head</hi> 7th, 8th, <hi>before-going.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When the Fox Preaches, beware Geese. When <hi>R. D.</hi> or his Emissaries come to Preach, know your Souls are in great danger.</p>
               <p n="18">18. 'Tis <hi>great comfort to us when we are weak in Faith, that Christ is then strongly believing in Heaven for us;</hi> and <hi>when we are weak in Love, that Christ is then strongly loving in Heaven for us.]</hi> This he Preach'd at <hi>Wellemb.</hi> as we have a certain Information. But this Doctrine is contrary to <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.14. <hi>By one Offering he hath perfected for ever them that are sanctified;</hi> therefore to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend Christ is still meriting in Heaven for us, (as believing for us, and loving for us, is meriting for us) it makes Christ's meritorious work on Earth incompleat, and imperfect, and destroys the very whole foundation of the Gospel at once. For the Gospel, and the whole of our Salvation is bottomed on Christ's perfect satisfaction on Earth; all was there finished, <hi>John</hi> 17.4. <hi>I have finished the Work,</hi> &amp;c. His Obedience and Sufferings were perfected, yea he could not come out of Prison without paying the utmost Farthing. One of his Preachers has lately brought <hi>Hebr.</hi> 2.12. to prove it, [<hi>I will declare thy name to my Brethren,</hi> &amp;c.] which demonstrates it as cleverly, as if to prove a Man a fit Preacher to the <hi>Davisites,</hi> you must first prove him an Ass, or an Idiot. You may see, Reader, how our Lord Christ finished the whole work of our Redemption that the Father gave him to do. And when he came to the perfecting stroak, he declares all finished.</p>
               <p n="19">19. <hi>[That there are several genuine senses of one and the same Scripture.]</hi> This he asserted before several Ministers. What, <hi>R. D.</hi> do you mean a Welsh sence, and an English sence, a Greek sence, and a Hebrew sense? Yet put on your Spectacles, and you may see them (I hope) to be all but one and the same.</p>
               <p n="20">20. <hi>Because he hath the Spirit, therefore the sense he gives of the Scripture is true, though never so different from the sense of other Divines: Such as</hi> Luther, Calvin, Perkins, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This <hi>R. D.</hi> also asserted of himself, before the foremention'd Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters, and all the Arguments they could use to the contrary, would not avail any thing with him. Thus <hi>R. D.</hi> is most plainly resolved to maintain his Infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, pretending he has the Spirit, and so he would make himself a Pope in this English Orb. Hence you may be assured by <hi>R. D's.</hi> Adherents, <hi>[That all that</hi> R. D. <hi>says is pure Gospel.]</hi> But what Spirit <hi>R. D.</hi> has, you may know by the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogue of his Lies, put down under Title 1st▪ Practices. Being Discoursed about the Five times of Christ's Intercession, by the Ministers that heard him, shewing him the Erroneousness of his Doctrine, and telling him the true meaning of that Scripture, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.32, 33. which he grounded it upon, <hi>He that confesseth me before Men, him will I confess,</hi> &amp;c. and that it is quit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> different from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction he made of it, and no such thing is implied in it, as he grounded on it,</p>
               <p n="21">21. <hi>R. D.</hi> made answer <hi>[I saw that in the Text too:]</hi> Testified by both the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters. This shews that <hi>R. D.</hi> is more quick sighted than the Quaker, (who proved <hi>Moses</hi> was a Quaker, from <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12.21. <hi>I exceedingly fear and quake</hi>)</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:206586:7"/>
               <p>While <hi>R. D.</hi> can see what he will in any Text, though the Text speaks of no such thing. And <hi>while he pretends he has the Spirit,</hi> and therefore the sense he gives of the Scripture is true, though never so different from the sense of all other Divines; and <hi>his People take this for greater Light than other Ministers have,</hi> and <hi>for purer Gospel;</hi> the Reader <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay discern what miserable case the poor <hi>Davisites</hi> are in, and how abominably <hi>R. D.</hi> deludes them. Yet you may have a farther knowledge of their case by the following Doctrines.</p>
               <p n="22">22. <hi>[Disciples grieve Christ, when they mourn for Sin.]</hi> This a Minister heard at <hi>Cambrige.</hi> And <hi>R.</hi> D. preached it up again, here in <hi>North<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>shire,</hi> as one of R. D<hi>'s.</hi> own Party has confessed. But is not this Doctr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne most desperately con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to 2 <hi>Corin.</hi> 7.9, 10, 11. Would <hi>Paul</hi> commend what grieved Christ? Would <hi>Paul</hi> say it was Repentance unto Salvation? and would <hi>Paul</hi> rejoyce in it, <hi>verse</hi> 9. if it grieved Christ? And yet these were Disciples, the Church at <hi>Corinth,</hi> and manifested the truth of their Discipleship by their Repentance unto Salvation. <hi>Now I rejoyce not that ye were made sorry, but that ye sorrowed to Repentance.</hi> verse 10. <hi>For Godly sorrow worketh Repentance unto Salvation, not to be repented of. But the sorrow of the World worketh death.</hi> verse 11. <hi>For behold this self same thing, that ye sorrowed after a Godly sort, what carefulness, clearing your selves, Indignation, Fear, Vehement desire, Zeal, Revenge, it wrought in you; in all things ye have approved your selves clear, &amp;c.</hi> And would our Lord himself look <hi>Peter</hi> into bitter Repentance, if his mourning would have grieved Christ. <hi>Richard Davis,</hi> this is a sign you are an Enemy to Godly sorrow that ends in Salvation. But where then will your high Presumption end, but in the greater Damnation?</p>
               <p>And are you not contented to ruine your own Soul, but will you thus be guilty of the Damnation of many others? Oh <hi>Richard, Richard,</hi> turn, yea turn speedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from these Heresies, and wretched Courses; before vengeance from the Lord strikes you.</p>
               <p n="23">23. <hi>[God is the ultimate Object of a strong justifying Faith, and Jesus of</hi> Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth <hi>the mediate Object of a weak Faith.]</hi> This he deliver'd in the foremention'd Sermon at <hi>Cambridge.</hi> Attested as the last. But this is contrary to <hi>Romans</hi> 4.23, 24. The same is the object of Justifying Faith to <hi>Abraham,</hi> a strong Believer, and the Object of Justifying Faith to us also, to all the Gentiles in general, weak, as well as strong.</p>
               <p>'Tis also contrary to <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.22. where the same is the Object of Justifying Faith to all without any difference. <hi>Even the Righteousness of God, which is by Faith of Jesus Christ unto all, and upon all them that Believe: For there is no dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference.</hi> The like in the 4 following verses. This Doctrine is also contrary to <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.14. <hi>That the blessing of Abraham might come on the Gentiles,</hi> &amp;c. But indeed 'tis ridiculous to fancy the object of a strong faith to differ from the object of a weak faith, in that general concern of Justification. But the more R. D. can me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamorphise the Scripture, the more sport he can privately make of the silliness and weakness of his Admirers. Questionless it affords the sweetest pastime to R. D. and his Comrade-Jesuits, to see how prettily these Sap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pates cluck under his wing, and admire and imbibe greedily whatever he delivers.</p>
               <p n="24">24. <hi>Christ and Believers are one in Intercession:</hi> This he delivered in the same Sermon at <hi>Cambridge.</hi> This is contrary to the nature of Christ's Intercession spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:206586:8"/> of before, and confounds that work which is peculiar to Christ; with those Transactions of his, wherein his members may be said to be included. Though Believers be one with Christ, who is the Intercessor, yet it doth not follow that they are one <hi>with him in his Intercession;</hi> no more than it follows, that because they are one with Christ, who is God blessed for ever, therefore they must be one with Christ in the Godhead; and so make Gods of them. But what cares R. D. if they will but Idolize him, as they did at one of their Deacons Houses at <hi>Wellemb.</hi> when they run away from Prayer to see whether it was R. D. came along when they heard the noise of a Horse. The man might pray on alone for all them, they leave Prayer, and run out to see whether 'tis their Idol sweet <hi>Richard</hi> that comes. And yet they are so grosly wicked in their way, that they begin to plead for that their leaving God and his Worship to go meet or see R. D. This some pious Ear-wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses of that Town assure us of.</p>
               <p n="25">25. <hi>Believers dishonour Christ by relying on Promises:</hi> This also he delivered at <hi>Cambridge</hi> in the forementioned Sermon. But doth not this make all the Promises of the Gospel void: And is it not a blasphemous opposing the great design and grace of God spoken of in 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4. <hi>Whereby are given to us exceeding great and precious Promises, that by these you might be partakers of the Divine Nature.</hi> Here the Devil appears in his own colours, and much like his appearance near St. <hi>Ives,</hi> when <hi>R.</hi> D. proposed this Question in his Sermon, <hi>[But how shall we know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther our Faith be true? You will say, by the word of God, but I tell you that will deceive you.]</hi> This is so desperate, as we could not tell how to believe, that he should dare to speak such things, and leave them so without explaining himself, 'till we had manifold confirmations of it. And yet <hi>Rob Benson</hi> one of his Journey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, came pretty near it at <hi>Burton,</hi> in these words (given under the hands of serious Ear-witnesses) [You will say how must we believe? <hi>God's word doth not tell us how we must believe, therefore if a Revelation of the Spirit will not satisfie you, we cannot satisfie you.</hi>] Well hit little Booby; when the World will bear 3 Popes, we'll get them to Proclaim Pope <hi>Dick,</hi> Pope <hi>Bob,</hi> and Pope <hi>Innocent. Dick</hi> for leading the People from the Scriptures plain sense, to his own sense; <hi>Bob</hi> for leading them from God's word, to Revelations; and <hi>Innocent</hi> for carrying them from the written word, to unwritten Traditions.</p>
               <p n="26">26. <hi>[To believe our Sins are pardoned, is justifying Faith]</hi> Deliver'd at <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge</hi> in the same Sermon. This Faith many thousands pretend to, while they live in open Prophaneness, Drunkenness, and all Debaucheries. But 'tis confuted by various late Writers. <hi>See Firmin, &amp;c.</hi> And withall see <hi>R.</hi> D<hi>'s</hi> great latitude, and why need any Rogue, or Villain in the World perish, since <hi>R.</hi> D. has gotten such an <hi>easie</hi> way for him to Heaven. Though it leads quite aside from <hi>Acts</hi> 15.9. The Heart purifying Faith. And 2 <hi>Thessal.</hi> 1.11. 1 <hi>Thes.</hi> 1.3. <hi>James</hi> 2.17, 18. But you'll discern <hi>K.</hi> D<hi>'s</hi> meaning better by the next Doctrine.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>[Faith is nothing but a Perswasion that my Sins are Pardoned.]</hi> This he added to the former. Here, Reader, you may perceive how this R. D. runs all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion at last into a meer strong Conceit and Fancy; which the most wicked pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fligate wretch will pretend to, and may have as well as any other. Then come away Chapmen, here's one of the cheapest Penniworths you ever met with; If you pass by this, you may never meet with the like, for ought you can tell.</p>
               <p n="27">
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:206586:8"/>27. <hi>Believers may not take comfort in the actings of their Graces▪</hi> Deliver'd in the aforesaid Sermon at <hi>Cambridge.</hi> This Doctrine is contrary to 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12. <hi>For our rejoycing is this, the testimony of our conscience, that in sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity and godly sincerity, not with fleshly wisdom, but by the grace of God we have had our conversation,</hi> &amp;c. 2 Tim. 4.6, 7, 8. <hi>For I am now ready to be offered;</hi> &amp;c. <hi>I have fought a good fight: I have finished my course, I have kept the faith, hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth there is laid up for me a Crown of Righteousness,</hi> &amp;c. Job 19.28. <hi>But ye should say, Why persecute we him? seeing the root of the matter is found in me?</hi> Psal. 18.20, 21, 22, 23, 24. <hi>I was upright, kept my self from mine iniquity, therefore hath the Lord recompenced me,</hi> &amp;c. Isa. 38.3, 5. <hi>Remember, O Lord, how I have walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before thee with a perfect heart, and done that which is good in thy sight.</hi> The Lord accepts his Plea, <hi>vers.</hi> 5. But no person must expect comfort out of R. D's way, if R. D. may rule the Roast.</p>
               <p n="28">28. <hi>Persons may sincerely desire Christ to be their Prophet, Priest and King, and yet be Hypocrites still:</hi> This R. D. Preached at <hi>Wellembr.</hi> and is attested by <hi>R. C.</hi> Surely R. D. would here make a trial of his skill, whether <hi>he could not pull hur to, and put hur fro, both;</hi> whether he has an absolute power over his Hearers fancies, that he can stave them off when he list, and bring them on again when he lists. Or whether one <hi>Welsh</hi> Jugler can't make fools of an hundred <hi>English</hi> Clowns? But what will <hi>English</hi> people be branded for ever for Bloc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heads, and never open their eyes, and kick him from among them? if they will not, let the <hi>Welsh</hi> Knave tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph over them. But take another with this.</p>
               <p n="29">29. <hi>A man may simply without self-designs and self-interest, aim at the Glory of God, and yet be an hypocrite still:</hi> This he delivered in <hi>Cayso</hi> side, attested by N. O. a judicious Ear-witness. In both these Doctrines R. D. wonderfully confounds weak Christians, as some have confessed. And besides he doth as notoriously oppose the nature of Hypocrisie, as if he had said, Sincerity is Hypocrisie. He also contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.29. <hi>Take my yoke on you, and ye shall find rest.</hi> Joh. 1.12. <hi>To as many as received him, to them gave he power to become the Sons of God.</hi> John 3.16. <hi>Whosoever believeth on him shall not perish.</hi> Thus those that take his yoak, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive him, believe on him, are the Sons of God, and shall have rest, and not pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish as the Hypocrites perish; therefore such as receive, Christ for Prophet, Priest, and King are no Hypocrites, no, but they are Sons of God, as we know Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites are not. 2dly, They that simply aim at the Glory of God, cannot be Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites, for God loves such, <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.17. <hi>I love them that love me.</hi> 1 Sam. 2.30. <hi>Them that honour me I will honour.</hi> Psal. 91.14, 15. <hi>&amp;</hi> 1 Joh. 4.19. <hi>&amp;</hi> Joh. 14.21. Simply to aim at the Glory of God, is the fruit of eminent love unto God. And such God loveth, but he loveth not Hypocrites, therefore they who so aim at his Glory are not Hypocrites.</p>
               <p n="30">30th. <hi>God th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Father a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> God the Son are at strife who shall love man best.]</hi> This he Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed here in <hi>Northamptonshire.</hi> Received from serious Ear-Testimony.</p>
               <p>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nother <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ime he expressed himself that, for the Language of Christ to the Father, <hi>[I will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> up my work of Redemption; if you will not give me th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>se]</hi> Whereas the Scripture <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d the Father, of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> own w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> gave th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Elect to Christ, <hi>John</hi> 17.9. I pray for them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> which tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> shall given me, for they are thine, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 1.4, 5. He hath chosen us in Christ, according to the good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>leasure of his will. Then here is no room for a strife between the Father and the Son: Men may not then suppose that the Lord Christ should use this kind of Language, though a Blaspheming Creature discourses at this rate▪ is not this
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:206586:9"/> Rashness contrary to <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.28, 29. Wherefore we receiving a Kingdom that cannot be moved, let us have Grace, whereby we may serve God acceptably, with Reverence, and Godly Fear. For our God is a consuming Fire. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5.2. Be not rash with thy Mouth and let not thine Heart be hasty to utter any thing before God, for God is in Heaven, and thou upon the Earth; therefore let thy words be few.</p>
               <p>We might add many more Assertions, Doctrines, and Principles of <hi>Richard Davis,</hi> such as these.</p>
               <p n="31">31. <hi>He would be a happy Man, that should break all the Churches in</hi> England <hi>into pieces▪</hi>] Hereby you may see, Reader, what <hi>R. D</hi> longs for. This he asserted lately.</p>
               <p n="32">32. <hi>Search the Scriptures, for in them ye think ye have Eternal Life, but ye only think so.]</hi> A sly confronting God's Word.</p>
               <p n="33">33. Make me as one of thy hired Servants, <hi>Luke</hi> 15.10. <hi>Is there's his Ʋnbelief, when God would have him a Son he would be a hired Servant.]</hi> How contrary is this gloss of <hi>R. D.</hi> to the Interpretation our Lord Christ gives of such Self-emptiness, and Humility, <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.8, 10. I am not worthy thou shouldest come under my Roof. <hi>&amp;c. v.</hi> 10. Verily, I have not found <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o great Faith, no not in Israel.</p>
               <p>Our Lord Christ tells us, such Self-emptying expressions are a Sign of great Faith: <hi>R D.</hi> says they argue Unbelief.</p>
               <p n="34">34. The Law gives a <hi>little</hi> sight of Sin. 2. A <hi>killing</hi> sight. 3. An <hi>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>pious</hi> sight of Sin.] This he dellver'd on <hi>Kimbolten</hi> side. Receiv'd from sufficient Ear-Testimony. This is like Doctrine 6th▪ 8th. and Explication of 17th.</p>
               <p n="35">35. <hi>There shall such go forth from</hi> Rowel, <hi>as shall sound the Gospel all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Kingdome▪]</hi> An Implicite overturning the Ministry of others, as if they do not Preach the Gospel. See Doctrine 9th.</p>
               <p n="36">36. <hi>God never design'd the offers of Grace should be made to all, but only to the Elect.</hi> This he asserted at <hi>Bedford.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But we hope here's enough about <hi>R. D.</hi> his Assertions, Principles, and Doctrines; or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, his Falsehoods, Errours, and Heresies. You may now take a taste of the Doctrines of some of his Journeymen, the Shoomakers, Joyners, Taylors, Dyers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which he has sent forth to Preach as an <hi>Apostolical Tribe,</hi> for <hi>Light, Number, Preeminence,</hi> and what not.</p>
               <p n="1">1st. The Doctrines of his principal Ape, that doth to the utmost imitate his Master <hi>R. D.</hi> in Cant or Tone, Phrases, Meen, Doctrine, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This Shoomaker he has set up to be Pastor to some conceited Persons in <hi>Wellemb.</hi> as we hear from such as live there: and his Name is <hi>Robert Benson.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. One Doctrine of <hi>R. B</hi>'s you had under Head 25. Gods word does not tell us how we must believe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>God commended that which</hi> Simeon <hi>and</hi> Levi <hi>did against the</hi> Sechemites, <hi>notwithstanding</hi> Jacob <hi>cursed them.]</hi> This he delivered in <hi>Tafts</hi> side. But if he would borrow new <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons out of the Apocrypha, yet he should have had the wit, or the honesty, not to take it ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of that par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which so notoriously contradicts Gods word. If <hi>Judith</hi> be brought in saying so<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> must <hi>R. B.</hi> go Preach it up for a pure Gospel Truth, before he considers how blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mously he thereby sets God against his holy Spirit, or indeed, against himself. <hi>Jacob</hi> by the Inspiration of God prophetically delivers those words in <hi>Gen.</hi> 49. <hi>v.</hi> 7. Cursed be their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger for it was fierce, and their Wrath for it it was cruel: I will divide them in <hi>Jacob,</hi> and scatter them in Israel. From the 3d. to 28th. is plainly a Prophecy indited by the special Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection and inspiration of God, as the <hi>English</hi> Annotat. Dr. <hi>Richards</hi> on <hi>Genesis,</hi> and others tell you, and as your own Eyes might plainly perceive. Now to make us if God commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Judith</hi>'s Mouth what he cursed by the Mouth of <hi>Jacob,</hi> is bals<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hemously to make as if the Great God contradicted himself, Oh Villany of Villani<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>But what would <hi>R. B.</hi> gather from hence? Answer, his next, words tell us, <hi>Therefore my Friend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> buckle on your Swords, and fetch your Brethren back from Idolatry.]</hi> I hope, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, you'l go along with them, and not put your Hearers to harder Service than you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l engage in your self. Therefore we conclude you have borrow'd a Sword to go with them, or you have got the biggest of your <hi>Awls</hi> to supply the room of a Sword.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:206586:9"/>3. <hi>They that die Doubting and Fearing are Damned.]</hi> This <hi>R. B.</hi> delivered about <hi>Ardingworth</hi> as Ear-witnesses are ready to depose it upon Oath. But when you lost the Honesty of a Shoomaker, did you lose your Humanity too, and become Barbarous? Surely more of the dearest Children of God die doubtful and trembling, than there are that die fully assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. See this third Doctrine confuted by Mr. <hi>Bolton,</hi> who proves the quite contrary in a set Discourse.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Christ tore himself.]</hi> This he delivered at <hi>Wellemb.</hi> in his Administration of that great Ordinance of the Lords Supper; having torn the Bread in pieces irreverently, as Dogs tear their Meat, <hi>R. B.</hi> added <hi>[Thus Christ tore himself.]</hi> Though this Doctrine could not be received from <hi>Fr. Cave,</hi> because he spoke too plainly, yet <hi>R. B.</hi> will try whether the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple cannot swallow it, when it comes from his Mouth.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>When we find our Hearts most wicked, then to believe in Christ is pure Faith.</hi> Confessed by one of their own Party.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>That there is no use of the Law.]</hi> This he deliver'd in <hi>Oundel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. That the 42. Chapter of <hi>Isaiah,</hi> Verse 19. is meant of Christ, that <hi>Christ was blind and deaf, and did not know what he should suffer, when he came into the World.</hi> But the Verse just before tells us who 'tis meant of, of wilfully blind Israel, and their Priests. See <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dati, &amp;c.</hi> on the place. And <hi>R. B</hi>'s Adherents at <hi>Wellemb.</hi> have vindicated it.</p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>That we are Adopted from Eternity]</hi> This he Preached on <hi>Kimbolton</hi> side.</p>
               <p n="9">9. <hi>People must not rest on Promises, and think to renew their comfort by them.</hi> And many more such.</p>
               <p n="2">II. The Doctrines of <hi>Heldebrand Rowlet,</hi> set up lately by <hi>R. D.</hi> at <hi>Kimbolton,</hi> who runs as despearately as his Fit-hearers, (as if some grand Devil drove them.) 1st. Persons when <hi>convinced, go to the Parson, and ask him what they must do to be saved; he tells them, Pray, Read, and Repent: But I say unto you, these are the black marks of Hell.]</hi> Preached about <hi>Welford.</hi> Here's course Language indeed, <hi>Rowlet.</hi> Beelzebub will pick out of any Trades those that have most Impudence, and will do him most Service. Joyners may be as help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in Satans Craft, as Shoomakers; especially if their Foreheads be lin'd with Brass enough.</p>
               <p n="2">2d. <hi>God justifieth the Ʋngodly in their Ʋngodliness.]</hi> This he asserted several times in <hi>Lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dington</hi> side, testified by a very intelligent Person at <hi>Loddington.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>He blamed the Church of</hi> England <hi>for not making Provisions for Persons coming to Christ, while they continue in their Sins.</hi> Ibidem.</p>
               <p n="4">4th. He told the People in his Sermon, that <hi>[He came to Preach up Faith: What, nothing but Faith? No, nothing but Faith.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5th. <hi>Doctrine the same with</hi> Campian<hi>'s Doctrine.</hi> Testified by sufficient Ear-Testimony.</p>
               <p n="3">III. <hi>Fr. Cave,</hi> 1. <hi>[Christ so loved us, as he</hi> killed, <hi>or</hi> murdered <hi>himself for us.]</hi> This, (though vindicated by <hi>R. B.</hi> in a smoother way, yet) makes Christ a Self-murderer, and so makes him a breaker of the sixth Commandment; and a great Sinner in himself, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by this Fellow destroys the whole of our Salvation at once: As well as contradicts <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.26. and Multitudes of other Scriptures.</p>
               <p n="2">2d. <hi>Christ raised himself from the Dead by the Power of his Humanity.]</hi> Both these he Preached at <hi>Bricksworth</hi> side, and in other places. But doth not this last ascribe also to the Humanity, what is the Prerogative of the Godhead; and giveth to the Creature an infinite Power, as the vain Papists do? Indeed, <hi>Cave,</hi> you had not gone to School to <hi>R. D.</hi> long enough, for here you plainly stretched your Arm further than your Sleeve could reach: But we'll forgive you, because of your Publick Recantation, so you return to Farming a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. <hi>Campian</hi>'s Doctrine. That <hi>['tis as gross Idolatry to Preach up marks and signs of Grace under the Gospel, as to Worship Sticks and Stones under the Law.]</hi> Testified by suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Witnesses. But how plainly this makes our Lord Christ and his Apostles all Idolaters, you may see by those places, where our Lord and his Apostles delivered and Preached up Marks and Signs, <hi>John</hi> 13.35.14.21.23. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>John</hi> 2.3.4. And the rest of the Scriptures mentioned above under Principle 3d.</p>
               <p n="5">V. Another Preacher near <hi>Langton</hi> in <hi>Leicestershire,</hi> delivered this, that <hi>[No Person ought to Pray, but he that is assur'd of his Salvation.]</hi> Testified unto a Neighbour-Minister by Ear-witnesses.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:206586:10"/>VI. Another at <hi>Wellemb.</hi> Preaching upon, or urging of that Text, <hi>Let him that thinketh he standeth, take heed lest he fall,</hi> 1 Cor. 10.12. Commented thus upon it, <hi>[But we stand fast, and are sure that we shall not fall.</hi> Thus you see, Reader, what an Impudent contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of Scripture these self-conceited Wretches are guilty of.</p>
               <p n="7">VII. Another Preached this <hi>[The Law is a Tree that bringeth forth corrupt Fruit.]</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>But now to <hi>R. D.</hi> and his Parties Practices.</head>
               <p n="1">1st. THey are given to notorious shuffling, equivocating, and lying.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Instances.</hi> 1. At <hi>Wellemb. R. D.</hi> was admonished of this, that he had in hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Sermon falsely charged, and railed against <hi>R. P.</hi> but he shuffled it off with a false pretence about his Intelligence; as a Minister there soon found out upon enquiry.</p>
               <p n="2">2. At <hi>Bricksworth</hi> being told of somewhat he had delivered just before in his Sermon, he positively denied it with a Lye. But <hi>R. D.</hi> have a care you do not so at <hi>Cosbr.</hi> lest that brisk Rector ruffle you more than all the Ministers thereabout, and catch you napping once again. Neither would we have you molest that little Bee of <hi>Wel</hi>— for he will pursue your <hi>Rowelian</hi> Cause most desperately if you do; and will tale out your Errors by whole dozens at a time, before all his People, till you let him alone with his little Hive. We wonder therefore that you should assault him. Yea, he'll sting like a Scorpion, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we think it a great Oversight in you, and your People, that you did not Flatter him with some of your Hony-words, as you did others. Doubtless your ruggedness with him has done your cause much harm, but above all be sure you come not near that dangerous young Spark of <hi>B—d;</hi> for of a truth he falls to Club-law presently, and gives you sore thump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing blows, when you have once moved him. These are three such notorious Desperado's, as no <hi>Rowelist</hi> in his Wits would assault them. [This is a Digression of choice Advice to you <hi>Dicky,</hi> if you would maintain your beloved Cause.]</p>
               <p n="3">3. At <hi>London,</hi> and in the Country both, <hi>R. D.</hi> reported, he had been before the Ministers of <hi>London,</hi> and they had nothing to say against his Doctrines. Thus he abominably belyed them.</p>
               <p n="4">4. A second time going to <hi>London</hi> about <hi>May</hi> 1692. with Lye upon Lye he got clear of the Ministers, till at last they followed him so closely, as he was forced to shuffle quite away from them into <hi>Northamptonshire.</hi> (Which see before.) But he feeds his People here in the Country with desperate lyes to the contrary, as some of them have discovered.</p>
               <p n="5">5. But as he was coming home, he brings a Lye in his mouth to a Minister, pretending his Relation at <hi>London</hi> advised to wonderful Accommodation and Communion. The Minister wrote to his Friend to know the Truth, and he assures him of the Falshood of it, and that he advised there might be no intermedling and interfering with each other's People.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>June</hi> 14th. <q>He told three Lyes to a Minister at <hi>Kimbolton</hi> Lecture, and several were ready to depose upon Oath, that they heard what he there impudently denied;</q> and did by positive Assurances convince him of his Lyes before many others. Hence you may draw a Proverb <hi>[A Davisite's Tongue is no Slander]</hi> A Davisite, that is, a Liar.</p>
               <p n="7">7. On <hi>Thorp</hi> side, when he told some Persons [<hi>All the Churches of</hi> England <hi>are gone a Whoring from Christ,</hi> &amp;c.] A minister asked him [Wherein is our Church gone, &amp;c.] <hi>R. D.</hi> shuffled it off thus [I did not mean yours.]</p>
               <p n="8">8. One desirous to know whether he designed to Preach at <hi>Kempston,</hi> as averse to such a dividing design, he assured him he would not; and yet next day he slip'd thither and Preached there, as Ear-witnesses assured. All Promises with <hi>Dicky</hi> are either broken or kept, you see. And thus <hi>R. Bens. Mansl. W. H-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n.</hi> and others, we know are addicted to Lying, though Elders, Grandees, Preachers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for the Sake of their Cause they'll lye stoutly.</p>
               <p n="2">2dly. They wonderfully bestir themselves to sollicite away the H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arers of other Ministers. This has been practised at <hi>Kettr. Oundel. Wellemb. Northampton, Bedford, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>2. R. D.</hi> and his Parties <hi>Visions</hi> and <hi>Revelations.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>YOU might perceive by Principle Fifth, how they lead People from the Word of God to Revelations.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>R. D.</hi> in his Sermon at <hi>Oundel,</hi> told the People, [He had had a Vision, and he saw God and Christ, and the Deceased in Heaven walking in her Uprightness] testified by several judicious Hearers.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In a Sermon at <hi>Rowel</hi> he told his Hearers, [This Morning an Angel of the Lord ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to me, to assure me, that we are in the right way, and he came to strengthen me in it.] Received from very serious Ear-testimony.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:206586:10"/>3. <hi>Robert Benson</hi> in his Sermon told his Hearers, [I see my self at this time as Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious as the Angels in Heaven.] Well, Reader, the higher an Ape goes, the more he shews his tail. Yet a young Stripling one of their Party, being discoursed about it, answered. ['Tis true, for I saw my self too, at that very time, as Glorious as the Angels in Heaven.] O raree Show! Satan's Spectacles are wondrous clear.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Others at <hi>Wellemb.</hi> have boasted highly of their <hi>[Visionary Faith]</hi> that is, they have so strong a Conceit of Pardon and Salvation, that their Fancies represent it as plainly to them, as if it were by a Vision from Heaven revealed to them. But Fancy boults bran, and thinks it flour. Let them have a care, for Fancies will not pass in the next World, though they abound in this.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>I. F.</hi> one of <hi>R. D's</hi> Hero's, saw the Lord Christ in a Room, or Corner, so plainly, as he would needs perswade another so, but he confounded the poor Girl, instead of clearing her eye-sight. This is well known among many of his Neighbours.</p>
               <p>Yea, what a multitude more have seen Christ (as they pretend, when they are admitted) though they dare not say, that they see Christ as plain as one of his Elders saw him one Evening.</p>
               <p n="6">6. And <hi>Rob. Benson</hi> must be in a trance, forsooth, and so have his Text handed down to him, if you'l believe him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>3.</hi> Their Ostentation or great Boasts.</head>
               <p n="1">1. YOU had one from the Preacher before, <hi>[But we are sure we shall not fall:]</hi> Take ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of his Preacher's Speeches to Mr. <hi>T.</hi> of <hi>Wellemb.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>[How simply will you look when Mr.</hi> Davis <hi>and I shall judge you at the great day?]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We wonder who reveal'd the Eternal Purpose of God concerning Mr. <hi>T</hi> unto this Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er: Or how came he to know that Mr. <hi>T.</hi> is a Reprobate, and shall die in his sins? Or that they shall judge Mr. <hi>K.</hi> of that Town, and all his People? We hope they'l spare some of them, and not be so cruel to these as they are to Mr. <hi>T.</hi> and Mr. <hi>K.</hi> for if we suspected they would, we should willingly take our Horses, and ride over, and speak a good word for some friends yet among M. Kr's People, before 'tis too late. Dearly beloved <hi>Davisites,</hi> spare that People whoever you judge, and we'll give you a fee for your kindness, if you'll let us but have it under your hands, before the day comes. Ah! you'll be of another mind on that terrible day.</p>
               <p n="3">3. At <hi>Bricksworth, R. Davis</hi> called other Professors, A company of Pharisaical, Hypocriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal (creatures) and at <hi>Burton</hi> the same; and at <hi>Wellemb.</hi> as bad, but with this addition, (at one <hi>Well</hi>'s House) a boast of his own great Piety, thus;</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>I lead such a pious Conversation, as I am a shame to all those Pharisaical Professors that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bear my Doctrines.]</hi> Oh brave <hi>Dicky,</hi> speak up for your self; but what do you live far from Neighbours? Yet, Reader, did not <hi>R. D.</hi> as plainly in this Sermon manifest himself to be a Pharisee, as the person represented in <hi>Luke</hi> 18.11.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Mr. <hi>Davis</hi> in his Sermon on <hi>Oundel-side,</hi> told them <q>[I was sick when I was about 12 years old, yet I was sure I should go to Heaven; but if I had died then, where would you have been; you would have lived in gross ignorance.]</q>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>J. F.</hi> his boasts, 1. [I am as perfect as the Angels in Heaven.</p>
               <p n="2">2. ['We shall work Miracles on Earth e're long.] Publick boasts before many.</p>
               <p>Fire, quoth the Fox, when he pist on the Ice. He saw it smoke, and reckoned there would be Fire e're long: Great expectations from a fond course, and from a fond Faith, these poor deluded Creatures have taken up, but not a whit better grounded than the Fox's ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of Fire.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>4.</hi> Their Admission of Members.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THey admit any that desire to be of their Society, so they bring not open Scandal up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them; therefore <hi>R.</hi> a Soomaker must stay till Harvest is over, for fear he should curse his fellow Labourers publickly again; and then they admitted him, as we are certainly informed.</p>
               <p n="2">2. When <hi>W. H.</hi> of the same Town was taken in, they asked his Wife her Testimony for her Husband, but she could say neither good nor bad for him, but only this [If you are resolved to have him, you must take him with all his faults as I did.] This several ear-witnesses attest.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Another, that had never heard <hi>R. D.</hi> before, but being perswaded by her Paramour, to come into <hi>R. D</hi>'s number; because she was a stranger to <hi>R. D.</hi> and he to her, therefore she
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:206586:11"/> desires one doubt to be resolved first; which was this [Sir, they say you are a Conjurer] but is it true? Thus he admits persons at their first appearance, before due inquiry.</p>
               <p>In short, Reader, you may know what sort of Cattle he admitteth, by these following instances.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>R</hi>'s. language to his fellow or Neighbour <hi>[There are seven sorts of Devils, and you have the worst]</hi> This is one of those he admitted, though guilty of a lye at his admission, as is well known by many where he lives.</p>
               <p n="2">2. By the swearing and cursing fits at <hi>Kimbolton [R. D.</hi> and his Emissaries gives the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to them that are in their fits; and one girl they brought the Sacramental Bread twice unto, before she were able to take it. Others near <hi>Kimbolton,</hi> dashed the bread away, and refused it, and yet these Villains forced them at last to take it, when they had no more sense of the greatness of this Ordinance than persons mad in <hi>Bethlehem.</hi> Vile Profaneness!</p>
               <p n="3">3. By the Maid at <hi>Archester,</hi> that put on mens Cloaths last <hi>Christmas,</hi> and went to marry another Maid about three miles off (at <hi>Bozeyot;</hi>) and for the diving faculties of her Fingers, her Father has been about to turn her out of doors: but she mattered it not, for she, holy Sister, indeed, was wonderful confident she should go to Heaven when she died; for so <hi>J. F.</hi> had told her, and she believed, and the <hi>Davisites</hi> at <hi>Wellemb.</hi> would entertain her if her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther shut her out; for 'tis no great matter with them to have fingers turned into lime-twigs.</p>
               <p n="4">4. By the man at <hi>Worlidge,</hi> who in his fit threw his hat at Mr. <hi>Davis</hi> while he was breaking the bread: Testifyed by Eye-witnesses.</p>
               <p n="5">5. By the Hurst-men, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that are grown enemies to Prayer now, though admirably great for <hi>R. D.</hi> and his Journy-men.</p>
               <p n="6">6. By their Abettor at <hi>Cambridge,</hi> who when the Maid began to be with child by him, went to marry her; but some stick not to say, the Devil walked before them in the shape of a Parson, and when he vanished they knew who it was. Of the truth of this some <hi>Canta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brigians</hi> can best inform the Reader, to whom we refer you. Such as these persons they have admitted, and do still.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>R. D</hi> admits young Children, that he may boast of them for eminent Converts, and make People believe he is the great Apostle; and these are the signs of his great success in his Work. But,</p>
               <p n="1">1. When the young child at <hi>Rowel</hi> was lifted up, and handed to the Lord's Table, and he asked her [Why she desired to partake of the Lord's Supper] the Child answered [That I may sit as a Queen in Heaven▪] Reader, you cannot imagine how great an Experience and Faith <hi>R. D.</hi> made this answer to pass for; having before taught the Children [That Christ's Lambs shall fit in golden Chairs in Heaven;] and such like fine toys that please the little Children: This we have an account of from the Confessions of <hi>Dicky</hi>'s own Party. But,</p>
               <p n="2">2. When he admitted two young girls at <hi>Wellemb.</hi> the Father of one did publickly oppose it, for fear she had not left the practice of lying, and so should become a scandal to them; but <hi>R. D.</hi> and <hi>Rob. Bens. &amp;c.</hi> over-rul'd the Father, and would have her in by head and shoulders; and so they had, much good may she do them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>5. Richard Davis</hi>'s Parties <hi>Self-condemnedness,</hi> as appears from</head>
               <p n="1">1. THE acknowledgment of some <hi>Davisites</hi> at <hi>Wellemb.</hi> That there are Errours among them; but they hope their Preachers are good men, and therefore they will adhere to them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Maid at <hi>Archester</hi> her Confession. That the Devil would not let her be at quiet till she did put on mens Cloaths and go.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Fit Maid at <hi>Brampton</hi> her assertion, That an evil Spirit haunted her; and we hear from a Minister that has been with her, that she had three quarters hang'd her self.</p>
               <p n="4">4. From the person at <hi>Moleworth,</hi> who also was forced to be watched day and night, lest she should make away her self: This she had gotten by her running after these Preachers.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>R. D.</hi> at <hi>Rowell,</hi> and <hi>J. F.</hi> were brought to confess, that the fits are disturbances from the Devil, and yet <hi>J. F.</hi> had but just before pleaded, that the sits brought great glory to God, and were signs of their eminent Conversion. And <hi>R. D.</hi> himself, we know indulges them, and makes much of them.</p>
               <p n="6">6. A Gentleman (a welwisher to <hi>R. D.</hi>) confessed, that [when he heard Mr. <hi>Davis</hi> spoken against, he could not forbear pleading for him, and yet his Conscience was not clear for him.]</p>
               <p n="7">7. A man on <hi>Willingham</hi> side being asked (if he recovered of his illness) whether he would
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:206586:11"/> go hear these Preachers, he answered [He knew he should not forbear going, though his Judgment were against it.]</p>
               <p n="8">8. Several at <hi>Wellemb.</hi> have owned, that they had such a strong impulse upon their minds to go, that they could not forbear going; though they found no inward Comfort and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largement when they did go. The same is confest by others.</p>
               <p>Though they own the fits to be disturbances from the Devil, yet they indulge them, (not only <hi>Richard</hi> himself pleading for them, and <hi>J. F.</hi> likewise; but the persons that have them, do indulge them. <hi>Instances.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. The Girl at <hi>Dorington,</hi> whose Grandmother would have her use means against them, and she will not, but on the contrary, she boasts of them, as Mr. <hi>Davis</hi>'s fits. A Fool will not part with her bawble for the Tower of <hi>London.</hi> Fits please fools, we see, though they would trouble wise people.</p>
               <p n="2">2. One of them going to Market fell into a fit by the way, a person that came with her la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting her case, [O, (said she) I am never better in my life, than when I am in my fit.]</p>
               <p n="3">3. At <hi>Kimbolton,</hi> one Lord's day, when <hi>R. D.</hi> preached there, a Pious and Judicious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son went to see him, and found the Room where <hi>R. D.</hi> was set, just like a Play-house, by the prodigious lumbering and rout of the Jovial Fit-persons.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>6.</hi> The <hi>Number</hi> and <hi>Quality</hi> of <hi>R. D's</hi> People's <hi>Fits;</hi> according to the best Observa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion Eye-Witnesses and Ear-Witnesses have been able to make hitherto.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THere is the <hi>Peeping Fit.</hi> in Sermon time peeping like Children at play. 2. <hi>The Smiling</hi> or <hi>Laughing Fit.</hi> 3. <hi>The Heaving Fit,</hi> these heave like a gorged Cat. 4. There is the <hi>Bark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Fit,</hi> spit in their mouths, and make 'em Mastiffs, for they bark bravely: We have heard them. 5. The <hi>Schreaming Fit,</hi> when they schream and shreek out, so loud as some have heard them near half a mile off; and so desperately, as if they were all murdering; one would think there were Beelzebub's Slaughter-House; or that he possesseth them for Swine: This is most in fashion at <hi>Kimbolton.</hi> 6. <hi>The Tripping or Dancing Fit.</hi> In this Blindfold-Dance they won't believe Satan takes them by the hand, though reason tells them it never so plainly. In this Fit we conclude the <hi>Rowel</hi> Girls are most expert. 7. <hi>The Running Fit.</hi> In this the <hi>Kimbol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> Girls excell the <hi>Rowelists;</hi> excepting that the <hi>Rowelists</hi> can run cross upon Beams best, like Rats; and the <hi>Kimbolton</hi> Girls do run fastest up and down the streets. For we are satisfied from several very pious Eye-winesses, that the <hi>Kimbolton</hi> Girls run as desperately as if some Master Devil drove them. 8. The <hi>Canting Fit,</hi> this turns a sober man's stomach, though the Inchanted Countrey People admire it. 9. <hi>A Sleeping Fit.</hi> But this is so silly and dull, that we do not question but they'll discard it, for those take best, that have most life in them. 10 The <hi>Swearing and Cursing Fit.</hi> When a Tradesman stopped one of them in her Fits, what lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, Reader, do you think she gave him? <hi>[Dam ye.]</hi> Thus, like Saint, like Fit. And yet 'tis observed by several that the rest of the <hi>Davis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es</hi> are so impudent as to plead for this Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Cursing Fit, telling People [Oh! they are light-headed.] But why will they not make use of such means, as the Lord has afforded, to help against these Fits: Yea on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, they indulge them, and boast of them. And wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reas 'tis certain Mr. <hi>K.</hi> soon ridded his number of them by the Lord's good help; why might not Mr. <hi>Davis</hi> hope for the like riddance if he desired it, and used means proper for the removal of them. 11. <hi>The Jolly Fit,</hi> as merry as Crickets, when they are to go from any other Town to <hi>Rowel</hi> to hear Father <hi>Davis;</hi> yea, as vainly jolly on the Lords day as if they knew not, or however cared not, what day 'tis; Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and Fools, live merry lives, but they sport with their own folly and misery. 12. <hi>The Brazing Fit</hi> of Impudence. 13. <hi>The Hugging Fit,</hi> the young Wenches hugging Father <hi>Davis</hi> as an Ape hugs a Puppy-dog. 14. <hi>The Gasping Fit.</hi> This we perceive must be called a new Fit for <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ky</hi> and his Preachers only. As when <hi>R. D.</hi> sets down in his Pulpit and falls a Gasp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and would you know what he gasps for, let him tell you himself <hi>['tis for the Inspiration of the Spirit;]</hi> that you may know he is no ordinary Man. But 'tis well <hi>Dick</hi> if you do not drink too much Brandy before you go up into your Pulpit, and then (to save your credit with the Ignorant people) pretend you breath for the inspiration of the Spirit, and so mock the Holy Ghost by your desperate tricks. There have many more observed how you handle the Bottle, than you have been aware of. 15. <hi>A Crying Fit,</hi> resembled to the mourning in the Valley of <hi>Megiddon.</hi> Thus Satan has many hooks to fish with, that if one takes not, another may. But the Lord in mercy undeceive these deluded Creatures.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:206586:12"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>7.</hi> Some things for the Country People to <hi>Enquire</hi> farther about.</head>
               <p n="1">1. WHether <hi>R. Davis</hi> did not really make a forcible attempt upon the Premises of the Wife of one of his Preachers? We could mention the Man's Name, and place of abode, but we spare him.</p>
               <p n="2">2. How many Sambanetto's and Bastinadoes he bestowed on his Wife, to keep her from tattling, when she had begun to blab it out, and might have spoiled her Husband's Dignity as a Preacher, while it hangs so much on <hi>Dicky</hi>'s sleeve?</p>
               <p n="3">3. Whether his Oyl that he annointeth Fit-persons and Sick-persons with (when the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons have a great Faith in it) be of the same kind with that which the Papists use in their Extreme Unction.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Whether <hi>R. Davis</hi> be not a Jesuite in Masquerade, seeing. 1. 'Tis certain he jugles and equivocates like a Jesuite? 2. He runs into Jesuitical Doctrines and Courses, and there may be many created J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>suites in <hi>England,</hi> without going to St. <hi>Omers.</hi> 3. <hi>R D.</hi> deludes his poor silly People like a Jesuite, and feeds them up with Lies. 4. He manifested himself to be a <hi>Jacobite</hi> a long while, by avoiding to Pray for their Majesties King <hi>William,</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> as multitudes have observed, though we hope his alarum at the last Assizes at <hi>Northampton</hi> has obliged him to it now.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Whether he hath not secret Converse with the Devil? For else how could he undertake and boast, he could Convert any ordinary Man at twice hearing him?</p>
               <p>We perceive plainly, that if he doth not make use of Charms, yet the Devil doth work under his Ministry with great Energy, that many have been, to themselves, and others also, unaccountably intoxicated. And have such a vehement impulse upon their minds, that they cannot forbear going again, and yet have no Rational, or Spiritual Conviction, Light, or Comfort, but a wonderful Confusion and Constraint, and some were almost distracted by going among them, as the Maids at <hi>Molesworth,</hi> and at <hi>Brampton,</hi> and that Maid at <hi>Dorington</hi> ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry near distraction, and many more such Instances according to Title 5th. Their <hi>Self Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedness.</hi> But when they keep clear from going to hear him, then they become well compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, as we know the Maid of <hi>Molesworth,</hi> and <hi>Dorington,</hi> and several more are, whose Names we would mention if it were convenient.</p>
               <p>Besides, the Ministers at <hi>Rowel</hi> Conference appeared to be Charmed, as one of them hath himself confessed. And how can he help some to Fits so speedily (as he has done, when they feared they were not truly and savingly Converted, because they had not those Fits;) unless he has some Secret help from the Devil? And what may the meaning of his Prophecy be <hi>[That the Legal Preachers will fall within Four Years time,]</hi> unless he either expected a Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of Popery, or he would amuse the People 'till Satan fetch him away, if he be a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>8.</hi> An <hi>Expostulation</hi> with an <hi>Advice</hi> unto the People of <hi>Rowel.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>YOU People whose Souls we wish well unto, Oh, when, when will you open your Eyes, and observe the horrid works of Satan among you! Were you once as a Golden So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, and now all covered with the dross of Heresies, Errours, Obstinacy, Pride, Presump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? What is all your Wine become, Vinegar? What is there none of that precious Seed left, that Orthodox and Pious Mr. <hi>Browning,</hi> so carefully sowed among you? what nothing but Tares now appearing? what a Garden of Christ all over-run with weeds? Consider also how many precious Souls you have ruin'd abroad in other Towns. Will you never en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour, and seek to get Pardon for your ruining that Person at <hi>Kettring,</hi> so conceited of <hi>R. D.</hi> his Oyl, as she might dolefully see her Presumption as well as <hi>R. D.</hi> his, before she died. Look upon that other Person that died in these delusions at <hi>Oundel;</hi> and have you not several more to lament for; we can tell you of more, if need be, who are already lost, and of Multitudes that are perishing under this Infection. And will you double your Damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? will you not be contented to go blindfold to Hell, but will you draw others with you? Oh! break off your Iniquities before Divine Vengeance overtake you, and cry for Pardon and lift up your Lamentation, and bitter Wailings, wherever you go, that others that are
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:206586:12"/> deluded by your means may take warning, and turn from these Errours and wicked courses, and cry mightily also for Pardon for themselves, and you both. Are there no Persons of understanding left among you? what not so much as a wîse woman to save perishing <hi>Abel,</hi> what not one to stand up, and oppose the encroaches of Satan; but do you contentedly suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the Inheritance of the Lord to be swallowed up by him. Are not some convinced of these Errours in <hi>Fenni-stant. Godmanchest. Cambr. Wellemb Oundel. Northampton.</hi> &amp;c. And have not they by the Lords help delivered their own Souls, why cannot you at <hi>Rowel</hi> as well as they? yea, are there not Ministers at <hi>London,</hi> and Ministers in the Country, that would furnish you with a faithful Shepherd to guide you in the ways of Truth, if you would make your serious applications to them for one? Do not these things shew that there is a possibility of your Recovery out of Satans hands, if you will but in good earnest set about it. And have you not great reason to set speedily about it, if you consider, that had you only murdered Persons unto Bodily Death, that Blood guiltiness would cry aloud a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst you? But oh, how many Souls have been, and are murdering through your means, through your harbouring of this vile Heretick, and through your sending forth so many to spread these Heresies and Errours! Oh, bethink your selves before it be too late, of what you have done, and how many are perishing through this Infection round about you! Can't you plainly see their horrid Presumption, or Presumptuous Faith, instead of true Faith. Don't you know that a Presumptuous Faith will ruine Men, <hi>Micah</hi> 3.11. <hi>Luk.</hi> 13.25, 26, 27. And are you not sensible also, that</p>
               <p n="1">1. That Faith which avoideth Scriptural Examination, is a Presumptuous and Delusive Faith; and such is the Faith of your party.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That Faith which cherisheth persons Indwelling Corruptions, and upholds them in a plain rejection of many a part of God's Will, is Presumptuous, Delusive, and a Soul-ruining Faith: And this the foregoing Narrative manifests concerning your <hi>Davisites.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Do not you know that the Faith that runs persons from God's word unto Revelations and Visions, is a false and delusive Faith? True Faith keepeth persons to God's Word as a more sure word of Prophecy, than all Visions and Revelations; if you believe St. <hi>Peter</hi> in 2 <hi>Epist. ch.</hi> 1.18 <hi>&amp;</hi> 19. <hi>v.</hi> compared.</p>
               <p n="4">4 And that the Faith that puts persons upon wresting the Scripture to their own Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, instead of subjecting their Consciences, Hearts and Lives to the plain meaning of God in his word, is a Presumptuous and Pernicious Faith. And thus we have shewn your Party does.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Do not you know that that Faith which <hi>pusseth up,</hi> is a Presumptuous Faith? <hi>Hab.</hi> 1.4. <hi>Luke</hi> 18.14. And do not your Parties Faith <hi>generally puff up?</hi> Else what mean your boasting of Light above others? Your trampling all the Godly Ministers under the feet of Contempt▪ What mean your Judging People while they are in this World? What mean your Rejecting the Doctrines and Warnings, and the much Honoured Name of your former Pastor, which will survive as a Name of blessed Memory, when <hi>Richard Davis</hi> and his Emissaries Names do rot? What mean the boasts of Perfection, and Glory like Angels? What mean such Boasts as these, [Now the Gospel is come to <hi>Lowick</hi>] and [there have not been so great Light in this Country for these forty Years] that is, indeed, never since the <hi>Antinominians</hi> were up here before, as some very well remember:) And [Oh! what a brave day has this been] (when the greatest Boasters, upon Enquiry, could not remember one Sentence of the Sermon so much boasted of!) Do not these things fully declare you have run People into a Presum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptuous Faith, a Faith that puffs them up with Pride? And,</p>
               <p n="6">6. Is not a <hi>blind</hi> Faith a Presumptuous Faith? And yet how many of these mighty Believers in your Party do not understand what they boast of? The Person that made that great Cry, that the Gospel was come to <hi>Lowick▪</hi> and when some of <hi>Burton</hi> asked him what Gospel, he was no more able to tell than a Child. And your principal Persons at <hi>Wellemb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rough,</hi> when they boasted of this great Light, and the Revealing the Gospel now: Upon Examination, what Gospel was come to <hi>Wellemborough,</hi> and what Gospel Tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hs <hi>Richard Davis</hi> preach<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d up, that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Godly Ministers had not before him? they could not instance in any one Gospel Truth. Don't these things show the blindness of the Faith of your Party, as making a great N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ise; and when Men come to look narrowly into matters, they find no new Truths, but only old Errors raked up, and newly broached by, <hi>R. D. &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:206586:13"/>7. Is not that Faith a presumptuous Faith, that <hi>People come so easily by?</hi> But your People boast much how easily they come by their Faith, in such Language as this, [What cannot you believe, 'tis easie to believe.] Tell them of Sin, and they'll believe away all their Sense of Sin; and believe Humiliation, Confession, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> all out of Doors: And <hi>R. D.</hi> preaches up this immediate Confidence, and tells them they must hold it fast to the end.</p>
               <p n="8">8. True Faith <hi>worketh by Love,</hi> Love to Christ and his whole Interest. Then were your Faith true, you dare not divide the Kingdom of Christ, you d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re not set up Faith to throw down Repentance; You dare not set up Justification and Faith against good Works; You dare not run Headlong into Errors, and withal so desperately seek to divide all Gospel Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: You dare not Idolize Mr. <hi>Davis</hi> as you have so often done both in your Speeches and Carriage, besides your running away from Prayer at <hi>J. Osburns,</hi> and leaving God's Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship to see Mr. <hi>Davis.</hi> You dare not continue any longer a Nursery of Errors, nursing up Plants for Hell. If you had true faith, you dare not continue a Fountain of Delusions, to send forth such poisonous Streams; and dare not serve Satan under a pretence of serving Christ. If your Faith were true, you would throw away your Vizards and Masking pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences; you would turn from these works of Darkness, and reform speedily upon this plain Call, and you would mourn for your Ambition and Pride, that brought you into this sad Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>; and mourn for your Idolatrous cleaving to a Creature, and to your own Fancies, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stead of God and his Word. And you will take this following advice to wash away your Guilt (as much as is possible.)</p>
               <p n="1">1. In the sense of your Blood-guiltiness, and your great Backsliding from God and his Truths, you will speedily spue out from among you with utter abhorrence; that vile Deceiver of Souls, <hi>Richard Davis,</hi> with all his Preachers, and all those that stickle for them: Or you will immediately gather together all that have any sparks of true fear of God in them, and would utterly withdraw from him and his wicked Party, who have been such unaccountable Snares to the Society at <hi>Rowel;</hi> and would bind your Souls in a solemn Engagement, to turn from all those Errors, and Wickednesses, unto the Truths and ways of the Living God, in and through the Lord's help.</p>
               <p n="2">2. You would set apart a day for most solemn <hi>Humiliation</hi> of your Souls before the Lord for your Sins, that have brought you into this deplorable Condition; and would call in the <hi>Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Ministers</hi> and Neighbours to join in the Work, and to be Witnesses between the Lord and you; of your serious <hi>Renunciation</hi> of those Errors, and your publick and solemn returning to the Lord; that the Lord may yet look upon you, and rejoyce over you to do you good; and for your obtaining, through the blood of Christ, pardon yet at last.</p>
               <p n="3">3. You would send <hi>Letters</hi> of <hi>Confession,</hi> and <hi>Humiliation,</hi> and <hi>warning</hi> against these Hereticks, unto those Towns and Villages, which through your means have been Infected; and where any Souls are yet perishing by the Infection.</p>
               <p n="4">4. You would hear none of them any more, nor converse with any of their Adherents any more familiarly (as much as you are able to avoid it) lest they should flatter or perswade you back into the Snares of the Devil.</p>
               <p n="5">5. You would immediately use the utmost diligence, to get such a Pastor among you, as is sound in the Faith, and abhors Errors; and you would earnestly invite in all the Ministers about you, to Preach there by turns, till you can get such a faithful Shepherd to settle among you. And the Ministers about you several of them we hear, would do the utmost to assist and serve you in so great a Concern, for the Glory of Christ's Truths, and the Salvation of Souls.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Those that have not an Opportunity to assist publickly, as Women, and Servants un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Yoke, yet by all manner of means they can find, they would promote this great, pious and acceptable Work of a solemn and effectual Reformation, and that the Lord may give you all Grace thus to act for God, for his Truths, for your own, and for others Salvation, hath been continually, and shall still be</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Our hearty Request unto the Lord on your behalf.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:206586:13"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>